# New Delhi, India +91 9899 46 96 86 nishi.in@gmail.com

# Nishant Agrawal

Technical, Solution, and Data Science Architect

github.com/root-nishi linkedin.com/in/agrawalnishant

A programmer and a leader having skills and experience in **data engineering**, analysis and design of **technical solutions**, and **pre-sales** consulting.

Having 11.5 years of experience in J2EE, of which 5 years has been in design and architecture roles.

### **Technical Skills**

- Languages: Java, JavaScript, Python, Pandas, Numpy and PLSQL
- Frameworks: Scikit-learn, Spring, MVC / MVVM, JPA, Lucene / SOLR, OSGI, Akka, JAX-RS
- DB / Servers: MongoDB, Oracle, Postgres, MySQL, JBoss, Weblogic, Apache, Tomcat
- Others: JMS, ActiveMQ, Git, SVN, Docker / Vagrant, Web Services, Enterprise Architect, Visio.

**Domains:** B2B, Insurance, Travel, Logistics, CRM, Asset Management

# **Recent Projects**

#### Prediction for Student Intervention

(Udacity, November 2015 – present)

- Analyzed problem domain and selected data for modeling the solution.
- Pre-processed data and prepared analysis models for prediction.
- Tuned best prediction model for performance and accuracy to 87%.

# **B2B** Logistics Portal Upgrade

(Nagarro, October 2015 – December 2015)

- Consult with a bulk shipping provider's IT Team on cargo shipping and tracking system.
- Analyze legacy code, and understand evolving business and technical needs.
- Propose technical / commercial plan for a flexible and easy-to-maintain system, that will reduce costs by 35%.

# Crew Meals Management

(Nagarro, September 2014 to November 2015)

- Analyze existing system for management of Crew Meals.
- Consult with Business Admins and Technical teams to understand requirements.
- Design the new system / integration points and provides cost estimates.
- Work with development team during implementation and delivery.
- Tuned performance to handle a load of 20 Threads-per-second with a response of under-350 milli-secs.

# Trade Automation

(Sapient, September 2012 – August 2014)

- Design framework for Automation of Fixed Income trades.
- Lead development team to deliver and tune automation parameters.
- Integrate with trading desks, and integrate with FX systems.

# **Work Experience**

#### Nagarro India

(September 2014 – present)

Work with development teams in proof-of-concepts, implementation, and delivery.

- Assist pre-sales team with technical solutions and estimations
- Code critical components, and do code and design reviews.

# Work Experience (contd.)

# Sapient Consulting

(September 2012 – August 2014)

- Provide technical leadership to Fixed Income platform development team comprising of 9 engineers.
- Contribute individually, review effort estimates, and prepare release schedule for various tracks.
- Improve performance and maintenance by application of better algorithms and data structures.
- Responsible for performance review and compensation distribution for development engineers.

# Infogain India

(October 2008 – August 2012)

- Technical Architect for Enterprise Integration and offshore development lead for a team of 6 engineers.
- Managed two J2EE integration agile project cycles for Auto-Insurance IT provider.
- Responsible for scrum, design artifacts, development plan, estimation, performance tuning, resource allocation, reporting and hiring.

# CoreObjects (Symphony)

(October 2007 – September 2008)

- Lead engineer for a team of 3 engineers.
- Responsible for technology selection, requirement analyses, design, development, and code review.
- Co-ordination with geographically dispersed teams for Zubican a US-based startup.

#### CSC India

(*March 2006 – September 2007*)

- Development engineer on Infrastructure team responsible for development of reusable J2EE components.
- Delivered enterprise integration framework for healthcare product and highly concurrent system for healthcare product of DST Healthcare Solutions.

# Infogain India

(January 2004 – March 2006)

- Developer for Imaging and Printing Group (Hewlett Packard) to provide integration solutions for CRM.
- Develop new J2EE distributed applications and port / refactoring / tune performance of existing applications.

### Education

*Udacity* – Machine Learning Nano Degree (in-progress)

Coursera - Machine Learning - Stanford Univ. (July, 2015)

*MongoDB Univ.* – MongoDB for DBAs (September 2015)

Aligarh Muslim Univ. - Master of Computer Science and Applications (76%, July 2004)

Aligarh Muslim Univ. - Bachelor of Physics (Honors) (66%, July 2001)

# **Honors and Certifications**

- Employee of the Month (Nagarro, 2015)
- Award for relationship building. (Sapient, 2013)
- Most Valuable Player, Mitchell International, US (Infogain, 2010)
- Best Employee at CoreObjects (2008), and Infogain (2004)
- LOMA 280 certified (2007)
- Scrum Alliance certified Scrum Master (Scrum Alliance, Pete Deemer, 2011)